## Valentin Lauret

# Statistical ecology & social sciences PhD University of Montpellier, CEFE - CNRS

Research interest: My research focuses on applied biodiversity conservation, with a particular interest in interdisciplinary approaches using statistical ecology and social sciences to work with managers and public policies.



## **EXPERIENCE**

Sep 2018- Oct 2021

#### PhD thesis

Ecological monitoring in Marine Protected Areas of the French Mediterranean Sea, an interdisciplinary approach about bottlenose dolphins with Olivier Gimenez, University of Montpellier, CEFE-CNRS

Jan - Jun 2018

## Student research project

Exploring adaptive monitoring for protected areas with Olivier Gimenez, University of Montpellier, CEFE-CNRS

Aug - Dec 2018

## Student research project

Understanding human dimensions associated with rodent outbreaks in Spain with Beatriz Arroyo, Robert Mougeot, and Miguel Delibes-Mateos, IREC-CSIC-UCLM, Ciudad-Real, Spain

Jan - Jun 2017

#### Msc thesis

Using opportunistic and uncertain data to study wolf recolonization in France with Julie Louvrier and Olivier Gimenez, University of Montpellier, CEFE-CNRS

Feb - Jun 2016

### 1st year Msc internship

Applying multi-scale habitat suitability models to the Mexican Spotted Owl in Southwestern USA

with Samuel A. Cushman and Ho Yi Wan, Rocky Mountain Research Station, U.S. Forest Service, Flagstaff, Arizona, USA

Jun - Aug 2015

### **Bsc internship**

Citizen science and the urban flora of Scotland with John Grace, University of Edinburgh, Botanical Society of Scotland, Edinburgh, Scotland

## **EDUCATION**

2018-2021

## PhD in Population biology and Ecology

Ecological monitoring in Marine Protected Areas of the French Mediterranean Sea, an interdisciplinary approach about bottlenose dolphins
University of Montpellier, France

2015-2017

### Master degree in Biological sciences

Ecole Normale Supérieure de Lyon, University of Lyon, France

2014-2015

## Bachelor degree in Geosciences, Paleontology, Evolution

Ecole Normale Supérieure de Lyon, University of Lyon, France

2012-2014

### Preparatory classes for engineering schools

Biology, Chemistery Physics, Mathematics, and Earth Sciences Lycée Joffre, Montpellier, France

2012

French high school diploma

Valence, France

## **ADDITIONAL SKILLS**

## Languages

French, English, and Spanish

## Ecological modelling and statistics

Population dynamics, occupancy models, spacial capture-recapture, distance sampling Adaptive management & monitoring Spatial statistics Bayesian statistics

## Computer and code

Advanced R programming
Spatial ecology and GIS with R
Basics of Python and Matlab
Reproductible science and code with
Markdown and Git
MCMC optimization with JAGS and
NIMBLE

## Scientific field work

2019, 2020, 2021
French Mediterranean Sea
Bottlenose dolphins
photo-identification expedition
3 weeks at-sea for marine mammals
monitoring

2018, Castilla y Léon, Spain **Leading social interviews** with farmers, hunters, conservationists, and members of local government

2017, Arizona, USA **Monitoring Mexican Spotted Owl** nesting sites in the Grand Canyon National Park

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### 2019

Organizing inter-professionnal working groups to identify bottlenose dolphins priorities in the Mediterranean Sea

INTERACT project with MIRACETI NGO, Nice, France

#### 2019, 2020, 2021

Teaching photo-identification monitoring of bottlenose dolphins to Marine Protected Areas managers of the French Mediterranean Sea TURSMED projects with MIRACETI NGO, French Mediterranean Sea

2018-2019 2019-2020

Ecology, concepts and methods: 40h for 2nd year Bsc students in Population biology

Conducting experimental ecology projects, discovering scientific writing, population biology, evolution

University of Montpellier

2018-2019 2019-2020

Basics in data processing and biostatistics for biologist: 32h for 1st year Msc students in Ecology and Evolution

Initiation to statistics, R programming, linear models University of Montpellier

## **PUBLICATIONS**

Have a look on Scholar



Labach, H., Azzinari, C., Barbier, M., Cesarini, C., Daniel, B., David, L., Dhermain, F., Di-Méglio, N., Guichard, B., Jourdan, J., Lauret, V., Robert, N., Roul, M., Tomasi, N., & Gimenez, O. (2021). Distribution and abundance of common bottlenose dolphin (tursiops truncatus) over the french mediterranean continental shelf. *Marine Mammal Science*, *n/a*. https://doi.org/10.1111/mms. 12874

- Lauret, V., Delibes-Mateos, M., Mougeot, F., & Arroyo-Lopez, B. (2020). Understanding conservation conflicts associated with rodent outbreaks in farmland areas. *Ambio*, *49*(5), 1122–1133. https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-019-01256-0
- Lauret, V., Labach, H., Authier, M., & Gimenez, O. (2021). Using single visits into integrated occupancy models to make the most of existing monitoring programs. *Ecology*. https://doi.org/10.1002/ecy.3535
- Lauret, V., Labach, H., Turek, D., Laran, S., & Gimenez, O. (2021). Spatial integrated models foster complementarity between monitoring programs in producing large-scale ecological indicators. *Under Review in Animal Conservation*. https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.02.01.429097
- Louvrier, J., Duchamp, C., Lauret, V., Marboutin, E., Cubaynes, S., Choquet, R., Miquel, C., & Gimenez, O. (2018). Mapping and explaining wolf recolonization in france using dynamic occupancy models and opportunistic data. *Ecogra-phy*, *41*(4), 647–660. https://doi.org/10.1111/ecog.02874
- Wan, H. Y., McGarigal, K., Ganey, J. L., Lauret, V., Timm, B. C., & Cushman, S. A. (2017). Meta-replication reveals nonstationarity in multi-scale habitat selection of mexican spotted owl. *The Condor*, 119(4), 641–658. https://doi.org/10.1650/CONDOR-17-32.1

## **TALKS**

2021

## **Euring Analytical Meeting**

Integrated spatial model to produce large scale ecological indicators Virtual meeting

2019

#### **World Marine Mammals Conference**

Combining multiple surveys increases precision and provide more reliable mapping of marine mammals distribution

Barcelona, Spain

2018

## **Pathways: Human Dimensions of Wildlife Conference**

Using Q-method for understanding conservation conflicts: common voles in Spanish farmlands Oral presentation performed by Beatriz Arroyo on my behalf https://digital.csic.es/handle/10261/175502